Hi, if you're like me, you spent hours scrolling on TikTok or Pinterest looking at Minecraft
building ideas without the intent to ever actually build them. Now, I don't know about
you, but sometimes inspiration just randomly hits. And I have to play Minecraft. Like,
that's all that's on my mind. And lately I've been seeing a whole lot of cottagecore Minecraft
content circulating around the internet, getting a lot of views. And so I downloaded some shaders
and launched Minecraft at like 6fps and built this for nostalgia. And if you're like literally
any person who's played Minecraft over the years, these houses were the bomb.
They were like move-in ready. Of course, there was only room for like three things to fit in there.
And then there was this problem. It's Minecraft cottagecore aesthetic because the mushroom
houses with this aesthetic are like next level. They are chef's kiss. They are immaculate.
And suddenly your wiki how tutorial on how to make simple mushroom houses featuring acacia
plank flooring are more an aesthetic than the 2013 mustache trend. And if this strangely specific
scenario applies to you, then boy will you like this tutorial. So now I present three ways to
make mushroom houses in Minecraft. Yay. So the first house is pretty easy. You're gonna want
to start out with a statistically impossible mushroom in the middle of a field and use bone
meal to make it big. Now stare at that mushroom until you decide to mutilate it to look aesthetic
like this. I wanted the mushroom to look a bit different than the other simple mushroom houses
you typically see, so I went for a more of a bell-shaped curve for the top of the mushroom.
You could also use one of those mini water bottles for reference. I modeled mine based
on an upside down flower pot and I think it turned out pretty good. Once you have achieved
maximum upside down flower pot conformity, then you can start modifying the stem to make it look
stalkier. I used the mushroom stem block and smooth quartz stairs. And if you're in survival,
you'll probably want to mine a few of the big mushrooms with a silk touch axe to get the
materials for this. I used birch plank flooring to match the rest of the interior. Now I really like
this house, but there's not much room. Sorry for my spore sense of humor. Here's the big grand
reveal of this house. Very simple, I give it a 8 out of 10. Next house. This is a little bit more
difficult than the last one, and so you're gonna start out by making a frame that looks like the
outline of a handmade cube of play-doh. The kind that the edges never seem sharp enough. And then
start sculpting it to look like the body of this absurdly priced plastic mini mouse teapot I found
on Amazon. I used smooth quartz blocks, slabs, and stairs to accomplish this. And if you want to use
mushroom stem blocks, I'm sure you could, but I just like quartz because it makes the mushroom
stem seem smooth and continuous, sort of like a differentiable equation. Also because it's not a
pain to get all those stems. After this, start making the stem taller to look almost like a BB-8,
and then give the wannabe BB-8 some helicopter blades. These will be the radius of your circular
mushroom cap. Then connect those little helicopter blades to form a circle. Also, I never really found
these graphs useful. I always find them on like TikTok. But then again, I always just wing it, and
it doesn't look very circular, so maybe they're helpful to you, but mine turned out pretty great
in the end. Anyway, start outlining the circle in red mushroom blocks, and then be indecisive, and
then decide on making the easy way out, and make a circular spherical looking mushroom cap. Mine is
about six blocks tall, and unlike me, you probably want to make sure there's no weird blocks left
exposed. Then I made the door and the window, and outlined them in the most superior wood type,
spruce wood. I used planks, fences, and stairs, as well as oak leaves for the window boxes.
To add some extra whimsy, you can make a dilapidated cobblestone chimney, and drape that
with oak leaves. To add some stuff to the interior, I connected the chimney to a fireplace furnace
type thing, and then added an unnecessary amount of bookshelves and leaves, because when in doubt,
add oak leaves and bookshelves. That's my motto. Also, I used flower pots, turtle eggs, and sea
pickles for the inside, and then I discovered that in 1.16.5, you can place turtle eggs on flower
pots, which is kind of weird. Anywho, I used vines as a ladder to the attic area, which will be a cute
little bedroom. I outlined the roof with spruce wood, and then placed some bookshelves behind them.
This would also be a cool enchanting room, but the house demands a bedroom, so I added in a
skylight, which looks good with the shaders, and I'm sure it would look good without them.
So this is the finished build. It only took me about 45 minutes to do in creative, so not too bad.
Ta-da!
Right, on to the last one. This one is kind of hard, but not like Pryor Gaming at the end of
his TikToks kind of hard. You're gonna want to start out with a circular base like such,
and then add a small circle attached to it. Once you have your two little circle buddies,
start making them taller and rounder. I focused on the bigger circle first,
because it's going to be the centerpiece for the build. Also, if this video gets 100 likes,
I'll make a video of my little sister following this tutorial to see how she does, because she's
bad at building and I'm bad at explaining things. Okay, back to the tutorial. If you don't know
what shape to make the base of the big mushroom, I referred to the gourd from the 2007 Disney
classic, Secret of the Magic Gourd, and mine turned out pretty alright. Also, I need to know,
was anyone else low-key traumatized by that movie? Because when I first saw that movie,
I guess I just thought gourds were strange pumpkins, so for the longest time, I was
fundamentally confused on what gourds were. So anyway, you're going to start making another
one of those helicopter circle things, and here's a better explanation using calculus,
if you want to know how to make circles in Minecraft. Presenting, building circles, yay!
So you're going to want to start out with this sort of graph paper, just trace something circular
onto it, and then fill in the blocks that the circle crosses. Make sure it all has the same
radius, and then this is where the calculus comes in. If you look at tangent lines, you know what
tangent lines are, I hope. You probably don't, but the slope of the tangent line is sort of the slope
of if you were to draw the slope through the, like, the grid squares of the circle. This made a lot
more sense inside my head, but you can trace pretty much any circle on the graph paper and
repeat this process, just make sure the radius is the same and that each quadrant is the same,
and there you go, you have a circle in Minecraft. Okay, now moving on to our other little mushroom
buddy, you're going to want to make him a wonky little mushroom that sort of stems off from the
big one. It's really hard to explain how I did this, but I would recommend using organic shapes
and have the top of the mushroom thinner than the base, then add a tiny little cap.
For the top of the big mushroom, I basically did the same thing as I did for the medium tutorial,
and despite it being vastly bigger, the cap is about the same height, maybe even five blocks
this time. I kind of wanted to make it sort of squishy like the first build, but I lost all my
brain cells thinking about calculus. If you want the mushroom to be super cottagecore, you can add
some birch leaves that hang like vines and some hanging lanterns. You could also use shroom lights.
I also added a dilapidated chimney to match the vibe, and then for the interior, I started again
by connecting the fireplace to the chimney and built a loft area with a ladder leading up to it,
and then I got distracted by a wandering trader and quickly resumed my work, and I used an absurd
amount of birch leaves to decorate. If you can't tell from my Pinterest page, birch leaves are my
favorite. Also, if you're wondering how they move in the wind, that's the shaders, and I use BSL
shaders. As far as I know, they only work for Java edition. I made a little kitchen space in front of
one of the windows, complete with some cake and some turtle eggs, and then added some seating by
the fire. In front of the other window, I made what HGTV calls a breakfast nook, complete with
some plants. While the bedroom space is smaller than the previous build, I think it turned out
nicely and I wouldn't mind living there. After decorating the bedroom, I remembered there was a
bunch of empty space in the loft, which I promptly decorated with barrels because that can be
practical when they're not converting all the villagers to fishers, and I did notice I accidentally
made a sort of shrine to Pinocchio, which is cool, I guess. On the outside, I was going for a house-ish
entrance, but I ended up making it more like a hobbit hole with spruce trapdoors and slabs and
stairs. I also added some dark oak for better contrast and ended up expanding the windows
downward because it just looked better. I added some shutters to the bedroom window and shroom
lights to better illuminate it at night. There was something that was still missing, though, and I
couldn't decide what to do, so I tried this thing I saw on TikTok where you make mushrooms out of
end rods and mushroom blocks, which I was a bit skeptical of, but I really liked how they turned
out. So yeah, those are three mushroom houses you could easily build in Minecraft. Comment below
which one you'd live in. I know I definitely would pick the second one because of the skylight, but
that's just me. And if you enjoy this content and would like to see more dollar store green tutorials,
please feel free to hit subscribe. See y'all later, bye!